ONE SMALL STEP FOR MAX

Dan Simmons

Introduction

(from Omni Best Science Fiction Two)

Born in Peoria, Illinois, Dan Simmons now lives in Colorado. His first published story appeared in Twilight Zone Magazine, as co-winner of the first Twilight Zone Magazine short story contest in 1982. His second published story, “Eyes I Dare Not Meet in Dreams” (Omni, Sept. 1 982), was one of the first stories I bought for Omni as fiction editor. The story has since been transformed into the novel The Hollow Man, recently published by Bantam. Simmons’ first novel. Song of Kali, won the World Fantasy Award in 1986; his second novel. Carrion Comfort, won the Bram Stoker Award in 1991; and his science fiction novel Hyperion won the Hugo Award for 1991. In addition to The Hollow Man, Simmons has another novel currently out, Children of the Night, about post-Ceausescu Romania and the plight of the orphans there. Omni has published several of his stories, including the novelette that eventually became Carrion Comfort, his epic novel on vampirism; “E Ticket to Namland;” and, most recently, the chilling “Two Minutes Forty-Five Seconds” (April 1988). These, and some of Simmons’ other short stories, are collected in Prayers to Broken Stones (Bantam).

In “One Small Step for Max”, published here for the first time, Simmons reveals his nasty sense of humor.

—Ellen Datlow

On the day that Max Kine first set foot on the moon, he had larceny on his mind, Interpol on his tail, and six gel-wrapped diamonds in his lower intestinal tract.

The landing at Matsushita City in Crater Moltke was uneventful, and Customs was cursory. The lunie behind the counter asked Max whether he had anything to declare, slashed chalk across Max’s suitcase, and waved him on. Max stood in line waiting for the maglev train into the city. “Merde,” he muttered, “swallowed the goddamn rocks for nothing.”

“What was that?” asked a startled Eurodame in line behind him. She wore a designer VR suit, but the blinking green diode on her peeper implants showed that she was tuned to realtime. She had a Berlin accent and that waxy, about-to-explode-from-tension skin that came from too many cosmetic bone moldings.

Max turned his brightest, most sincere smile on her. “I was just saying, Madam, that the word is that one can find some striking moonrocks in that gift shop for next to nothing.”

The Eurodame scowled at him until a limo door irised open for her. The magtrain floated in a moment later. Max stowed his luggage under his seat and watched the rocky plain of Mare Tranquillitatis slide by as he levitated his way toward Matsushita

City past billboards announcing that there were only one hundred days left until the Gala 75th Anniversary of the First Lunar Landing.

The Tranquillity Oberoi Sheraton accepted the imprint of his counterfeit universal card and Max checked into an aboveground suite, ordered up dinner and a bottle of FasLax, and waited to retrieve his stolen diamonds. The stones were his last resort—a currency for bribes that had saved his life and liberty more than once. Max had met few officials who could not be bought off with diamonds in a time of hyperinflation.

The way Max figured it, he had four days in which to score here on the moon. After that, the wife of the missing South African merchant whom Max’d left in a flashback parlor in Riyadh—the merchant whom he’d left grinning and drooling his way through Strange Loop recyclings of his first sexual encounter—would get Max’ s postcard, retrieve her spouse, and call the cops. Max thought of what five days of constant flashback Strange Looping would do to the human brain and sincerely hoped that Mrs. South African Merchant had a vegetable garden big enough to stow her hubby with his intellectual peers.

Four days to make a big score. Max pondered his options. With most crooks who had grown up in the New Age Global Co-Prosperity Sphere, crime was a subtle, almost cerebral thing; white collar embezzlement by breeding new tapeworms to chew their way down the sphere credit streams, or complicated Virtual Reality scams, or the occasional counterfeit universal card. Not so with Max. He had grown up in the Detroit Badlands, a hive slum which had known neither the New Age nor Co-Prosperity. During the Nipponese Reconstruction of the U.S.A., the new masters had decided that Detroit in general and the Badlands in specific were not worth reconstructing.

Various judges and personality-reconfiguration therapists had said the same thing about young Max Kine.

Max had always preferred direct action in an age of pissant nuance. Despite the fact that Max was a small man, almost gaunt in a whipcord way, his specialties had been in armed robbery, extortion, and kidnapping. Most North Hem hive cops, with their doctorates in VR sleuthing and Gibsonian matrix detection, did not know how to cope with Max’s type of one-man Neanderthal crime wave. Neither did his victims. By the time his kidnap victim’s spouse and/or significant other had shelled out the ransom—always in negotiable merchandise, never credit—Max was long gone. Now approaching forty years of age, Max could still boast that he had served no time since he was sixteen.

But things and people were catching up to him. His modus operandi was too well known, his haunts too well established now that he had used up most of the great cities of the North Hem. And Max hated traveling the Second World with its insane, nonprofitable violence and its cyberprick VR crazies.

So Max Kine needed one more large score before retiring, and the only place left with rich pickings was the moon. Most professional criminals were afraid of operating on the moon, afraid of the pioneer justice reputed to be the lunies’ swift response to even the most modest criminal act. Most professional criminals avoided the moon. But not Max Kine. Now, waiting for his diamonds, he sat in his luxury suite’s WC, stared out through the crack in the door at the huge crystal chandelier in his main suite, and read his Oberoi Sheraton Traveler’s Information booklet in hopes of finding some detail that would lead to his Big Score.

Americans had been the first to land on the moon almost seventy-five years earlier—this was one of the few facts that Max knew about the place—but almost a half century of eager American, EuroFed, and Russ Republic attempts at returning and colonizing had amounted to didley squat. A few rundown Quonset-hut research bases still lay scattered across the Mare like pimples on the moon’s big, pale behind. The old Russ observatory complex sat empty in Karpinsky Crater on the far side. Not much to show for fifty years and several hundred billion old bucks.

Then the Nipponese had grown interested in the moon. Not for science—the rate of return on pure science was pitiful—but in the tourist and recreational aspects of lunar colonization. In a world jaded by VR and flashback drugs and total access to almost anywhere, the moon seemed a logical place to extend the luxury resort philosophy of the Nipponese underwater Pacific resorts and the Mt. Erebus condos. Within five years of that decision, the moon’s population had gone from eighteen hundred forgotten researchers to more than a hundred and ninety thousand workers. Five years after that, the population was at twenty-five million and climbing. Tourists liked the place. VR could simulate the one-sixth gravity, and the flash of sunlight off the escarpments of Hyginus Rill during the three-day sunrise, and even the shouts and echoes at the Clarke Center Icarus Caves where tourists flew on feathered wings, but any hive dolehead could access VR . . . only the relatively well-to-do could go mooning and bring back the homemade holodisks to prove it.

At least it was true that the moon used to be a resort for the rich. Max scanned the tourist attractions. Lunaland Disney north in Mare Nectaris. The Honeymoon Grotto in The Sea of Fertility. Tranquillity Base Museum. The Bay of Rainbows Designer Outlet Discount Center. The Icarus Caves. The Sony-Tycho Pleasure Dome.

Merde, thought Max. Well, he’d just have to stick to the high-rent districts and find his Big Score there.

Four days.

Max retrieved his diamonds, polished them, dragged a table to the center of the main room, and set the diamonds in with the crystal prisms of the chandelier. Pushing the table back in place, Max frowned up at his hiding place. Usually he preferred having his diamonds within immediate reach; sometimes the authorities got surly if the bribe wasn’t immediately visible and tangible.

Max considered hiding the diamonds behind a painting or within the hem of the curtains covering the fake window, but then he remembered the light gravity that had him moving in clumsy lopes, as if he were underwater. Crouching, Max coiled and jumped. He almost smashed his skull against the ceiling four meters above him. Pushing off from the ceiling, Max twisted, managed to avoid smashing into the chandelier, tinkled the crystal as he dropped in slow motion, and landed gently on his feet.

No problem retrieving the stupid things, thought Max. He stood looking at the chandelier and thinking that he might need the diamonds to bribe his way off this stupid chunk of airless rock if he didn’t score in the next four days.

Four days.

On his second day on the moon, Max took the most expensive Sea of Tranquillity tour offered. He hated tours. They were for suckers and deeb feebs. Rich suckers and deeb feebs. Targets.

Besides, Max knew that he had to get the lay of the land. Robbery and kidnapping, his two central sources of income, required a careful knowledge of access and egress. Max was not a stickler for details—details tended to bore him—but when it came to his work, he usually paid attention.

The tour gave a fast overview of luxury recreation spots in half a dozen crater cities in Tranquillity basin: the Central Peak tidal pools in Torricelli, the Zen Gnostic meditation caves above Lamont, the botanic gardens in Maskelyne, the Sosigenas Spa, the Sabine-Ritter Links with eight kilometers of Jack Nicklaus low-g golf course, and the Arago Heights Extinct Species Safari. It was all bullshit to Max, but before the morning was half over he had chosen his victim.

It was the nosy Eurodame from Customs. She had exchanged her chic Tosada-Venturi VR suit for silk travel khakis, but her peeper diodes were blinking and Max was sure that she was enjoying the tour on every level VR could offer. She was old and traveling alone, and every time she flashed her platinum universal card, Max had images of the payoff from worried nephews and nieces back in Berlin.

It looked as if the snatch and disposal of the old lady would be easy enough—security appeared to be a joke with the lunies, and spacesuits and rovers were rentable if one wanted to get outside the city domes—but what about delivery of the ransom? Max had no intention of being stuck on the moon forever.

The tour was over and Max was swimming in the hotel pool when he saw a familiar face. Usually recognition was something that he would avoid at all costs, but in this case the face belonged to a woman he had known and lived with years before. She had even helped him with a Toronto credit heist before running away with an old accomplice of his.

She had not seen him as she walked through the pool area with her head down. Max pulled on a robe and followed. He noticed that she was wearing the green and blue outfit of an Oberoi employee.

Max followed her down a service dropshaft deep into the residential hive tunnels. The only illumination here was filtered sunlight through the occasional fiberoptic sun bundle. She did not look back before palming a door and entering her cubby. Max knocked and stared into the cheap watchdog lens, refusing to answer its queries, waiting for her to check the monitor. When she opened the door to let him in, she was also in a bathrobe, obviously ready to take a shower. Her eyes looked tired.

“Max. My God.” She stepped back to let him into the four-by-six-meter efficiency.

“Swoozie.” He jammed his hands in his pockets and paced the length of the room. “How you doing, Babe?”

She shrugged and tugged her robe tighter. She looked twenty years older than when he had last seen her four years ago. “What do you want, Max?”

It was his turn to shrug. “Flashback maybe? We could tune into Toronto, sixty-five. Share a trip.”

“I don’t do F any more,” she said. There was a bitter edge to her voice.

“How about some full-tactile VR, Swooz? Compatible alphas. For old times’ sake?”

“I can’t afford it, Max.” She twitched her smile again and popped a standard inhaler. “The hardware, I mean,” she added. “I could never afford you.”

Max plopped onto a padded bench. “Scotch then?”

She shook her head again. “What do you want, Max?”

“Why don’t you start by telling me why you dumped me for Wild Bill.”

She squeezed the lapels of her robe together. “He was decent to me and you weren’t. Next question.”

“What are you doing here, kid?”

“I work in the recycling vats in the Sheraton bio galleys.” Her eyes were almost blank as they turned in his direction. “One more question, Max, and then I’m telling the watchdog to call the cops if you don’t leave.”

Max smiled at her. “Don’t you want to know what I’m doing here, Swooz? What the past few years have been like for me?”

“No.”

His smile faded. “All right, last question. Where’s that miserable fuck Bill? He took half of my share from the Toronto job.”

Her mouth twitched again. “Bill’s in the Matsushita lunies’ loony bin. A padded cave about three hundred meters beneath here. He’s been there drooling and wetting himself for almost three years now.”

Max frowned. “Why? What happened?”

“Your questions are all used up, Max.” She reached for the door panel, but he grabbed her wrist and waited.

“Bill tried a simple Gibsonian matrix scam,” said Swoozie. “Just moving a few credit blocks around. Harmless white collar stuff. No victims.”

“And?” said Max, still gripping her wrist.

“And it worked for a few months. Then they caught him and put him in a Dante Suit.”

“Dante Suit?” said Max. “Like those VR suits the Shining Path Vindicators used before joining the Sphere? The pain-giving thing?”

“Exactly,” whispered Swoozie. “Let go of my arm before I scream.”

Max released her. “Why would that drive Wild Bill nuts? He could take pain. I remember the time that street punk used a welding laser on Bill’s arm in Detroit when we—”

“This isn’t just pain,” whispered the woman, “it’s pure pain. And they haveall sorts of settings . . . crushed kneecap, dental extractions, pins in the eyeballs . . . and they gave Bill three days’ worth of it.”

“Still . . .” said Max, more to himself than to Swoozie.

“Goodbye, Max,” she said and palmed open the door.

He reached for her, but she set her finger on the watchdog panel. He stepped into the corridor.

“Whatever you’re planning,” she said, “it’s probably stupid and brutal and short-sighted. Just like you.”

Max opened his mouth to answer, but the door had slid shut in his face. He walked back to the dropshaft whistling softly, his hands in the pockets of his robe. She was still crazy about him. He could tell. After his big score, he’d have her up to his suite for some flashback and introduce her to old times.

The next day he followed the Eurodame, Ms. Erma Schell of the clone dynasty Schells, as she visited Tranquillity Base Museum and the Lunar Landing Monument. There, half an hour into the tour, he forgot about her completely and found his Big Score.

The museum was way the hell out in the boonies, accessible only by tour shuttle. Besides the concession stand and the museum proper—a dark space filled with old spacesuits, photographs of some grinning 20th Century rocket yahoos, a yacking holo of some old astronaut yutz with thinning gray hair and a quirky smile—there was the Lunar Landing Monument itself.

Max’s interest in all this ancient history stuff was zero-zero. But as he followed Ms. Schell into the circular perspex torus of the monument, things began falling into place.

A recorded voice was droning, “Here, on July twentieth, nineteen sixty-nine, men from the planet Earth first set foot on the moon. They came in peace for all mankind. First down the ladder of the landing module was Astronaut Neil Armstrong—”

Max quit tailing his old Eurodame and walked over to the clear wall. Ten meters out on the bare lunar soil, protected only by a forcefield canopy overhead to keep micrometeorites from further degrading the ship and landing site, squatted the descent stage of the ancient and ungainly lunar lander. An old-style U.S. flag still leaned stiff and cockeyed away from where the ascent stage exhaust had almost knocked it over almost seventy-five years earlier. There was junk strewn around the open area—gold foil, bits of plastic, a camera knocked from an open bay on the lander, a lanyard, scraps of unrecognizable debris—but a spotlight illuminated the single item that caught and held Max Kine’s gaze.

“This footprint,” the voice was droning, “represents humanity ’ s first step from the cradle of planet Earth. Its value to the lunar community . . . and to all mankind . . . is beyond estimation. Protected and preserved here by the harsh vacuum of the moon, Neil Armstrong ’ s first giant step for mankind may last another billion years

The bullshit spiel went on, but Max was no longer listening. He was staring, and the intensity of his stare, if observed, might have reminded the observer of a raptor’s hungry gaze.

And Max was smiling. Broadly.

It took Max less than a day to case the place. Information was free on the comnets. In two days he had visited the museum and monument three more times, twice wandering into restricted areas. Security guards intercepted him, but they bought his story of searching for the restrooms.

“Security guards” was too strong a term in Max’ s estimation. During the hours the museum was open—eighteen hours of the arbitrary twenty-four hour “day” the lunies kept in operation for the tourists’ comfort—there were six rent-a-cop farts on duty. During the off-hours, just four guards and a handful of maintenance people. There was a central guard station, but it consisted of nothing more than video monitors that showed the interior halls of the museum and monument torus. The guards were armed with old-fashioned Malaysian-style stun wands.

Max turned his attention to access and egress. The former was a cinch; every resort rented rocket cars, moon buggies, and hoppers. The last was Max’s choice: a sort of bicycle rocket thingee with thrusters and struts and—as far as he could tell—almost absolute exemption from any traffic control. The lunies were civil libertarians to the point of callousness. If guests wanted to kill themselves, fine. The hopper couldn’t get enough altitude to get into the main transport lanes and the simple computer on board was just smart enough to avoid collisions with mountain peaks or other hoppers and to get the dumb tourist back to where he started from. Which took care of the egress.

Perfect, thought Max.

Max could rent a hopper in Matsushita City after dinner, be down at the Tranquillity Museum in less than an hour, do what had to be done while the museum was closed to tourists, and be back in his suite before the maid came in to turn down the sheets. Perfect.

Max studied maps and decided on the best place to stow what he would steal. There was an arroyo with a set of small caves about thirty klicks northeast of Tranquillity Base, far off any beaten tourist track.

The hoppers were not pressurized, so Max spent part of his third day renting a spacesuit and receiving instruction. The suit was idiot-proof: 36 hours of rebreathable air, self-sealing, computerized with its own simple navigation system, food slots in the helmet, and a Dr. Denton flap behind for a simple waste extractor.

Forty minutes into the lesson, Max grew restless. The instructor was droning on about getting lost. “If separated or the navigation computer were to fail—a near impossibility—don’t worry about being found. The rescuers will find you. Each suit—” Max keyed off his comm. He had no intention of getting lost.

The morning of his fourth day, Max took his rented suit and rented hopper out onto the Mare and practiced. First he found a gully far from prying eyes and stomped around a bit, leaving footprints in the soil. They seemed about the same depth and consistency as the one at Tranquillity Base. Then Max experimented.

He had brought a variety of tools and spray cans: trowels, shovels, plaster of Paris, fixative, flowfoam aerosols, boxes. It took almost two hours to find the right combination, but finally he was adept at digging around the footprint, spraying the cast into rigidity, loading it carefully in a flowfoam box, and tucking it into the saddlebag on the hopper. The whole process took less than eight minutes.

Max went back to the hotel and had a fine meal. Then he went up to his room, disassembled his Nikon imager, reassembled four of the flash components into a Colt deathwand, and velcroed it onto his black jumpsuit. The bottom of his camera bag came apart, and he removed a micro-thin layer of C-4-2 polymer explosive. Six microchips in the Nikon’s focus system clicked out to serve as detonators.

Max sat on the edge of the bed for a minute. It was his opinion that two billion dollars would be about right for this ransom. Not in credit, but in black market new bucks. He would wait a while before even announcing his demands from the safety of Earth—from one of the Fiji archipelago states perhaps. He thought he would let the panic build for a week or two after he headed Earthside, then get in touch via his usual traceproof one-pad back channels. The money could be shipped to an offshore bank, transported by mule cutouts, and would have to be in Max’s hands before he commed up directions for their little search teams. No harm done. Set for life.

Max stretched and looked at himself in the mirror. Then he went down to his rented hopper and flew south.

There were only four of the lunie-style personal rocket cars in the Tranquillity Museum parking lot. Max had come in from the north, skimming along only two meters above the rocks and craters, the shadow of his hopper and spacesuit bobbing over dusty boulders and looking like a clumsy doll stuck in a flying bedstead.

He jinked the hopper’s controls and set down on the roof of the museum. Hopping off his bicycle seat, Max pulled the deathwand from his spacesuit pocket, set it on widest dispersal, and walked the length of the building, spraying down through the roof. He did the same for the observation torus around the Apollo landing site. There was no defense against a deathwand; anything inside the structure which had a synaptic system more complicated than a grasshopper’s was dead.

The spraying had taken less than a minute.

Max pulled C-4-2 from his spacesuit pocket, tore off a piece, molded it into a lump, coded the detonator for 20 seconds, and moved back to the hopper while the explosive blew off a ventilator access cover and three layers of pressure seal. He stayed back while the atmosphere geysered out of the museum, littering the rooftop and surrounding area in a cloud of detritus: papers, loose office crud, a spacesuit glove from an open exhibit, cups . . . even a set of dentures.

Max checked his suit chronometer. Less than three minutes had elapsed since he had landed on the roof. He grabbed his bag of equipment from the saddlebag and dropped easily down the ventilator shaft, kicking open the remaining grills. Max landed in a corridor where loose garbage still stirred in the last wisps of escaping atmosphere, oriented himself quickly, and went to the guard station. The three security guards were in no condition to challenge him. Max was only slightly interested in the bubbling and boiling going on—he had never seen the effects of explosive decompression on a corpse before—but he wasted no more than a glance at the phenomenon before stepping across them and checking the security panels. Max Kine was an expert at security panels.

The museum computer had closed airtight doors throughout the complex. Max opened them with a manual override. He also turned off the polarizing forcefield above the landing site monument. Alarm diodes and holos were flashing, and Max assumed that he would hear bells and voices if there were atmosphere in the room, but a quick scan showed him that there had been no automatic radio calls for help. The computer was desperately trying to alert security people or others in the complex, but it had no program to call anyone else in the first five minutes of a disaster. Max checked his suit chronometer. Four minutes and eight seconds had elapsed.

Max lobotmized the security computer and bounced down the hallways toward the observation torus. He found the fourth guard in the central corridor and noticed several bodies through open office doors along the way—at least five men and three women—but it wasn’t his fault if these stupid administrators and maintenance people had come in to work at the wrong time. Truth be told, Max Kine had never considered anything to be his fault.

There were no bodies in the torus. Max took only a second to stare out at the Apollo historical site; then he set his second wad of C-4-2 shaped charge against the perspex window and blew an almost perfectly round hole in it. Max stepped through and bounced lightly across the lunar surface. Dust rose in slow, one-sixth-g arcs as he trod across the historical footprints.

For a second Max considered taking the flag as well, but then decided not to vary from the script. On a whim, he tugged the cockeyed flagstaff out of the gray soil and launched it like a javelin. The wire-stiffened plastic flag messed up the trajectory and the whole thing tumbled clumsily out of sight over the torus roof.

No more goofing around, Max warned himself.

It was not hard finding Armstrong ’ s first footprint; the laser spot still illuminated it in a golden glow. Max opened his bag and bent to his task. Trowels, spade, fixative, flowfoam. The whole thing took less than five minutes.

Max transferred the flowfoam container to his bag, tossed his tools in, bounced back across the regolith, and leaped easily to the roof of the torus and then to the top of the museum. He stowed everything in his saddlebag, tweaked the handlebar controls, and went skimming off a meter above Mare Tranquillitatis. The emergency and police channels were as silent as the tomb he had just left.

In the arroyo thirty klicks northeast along a low rill that ran out from a crater rim, Max parked his hopper on solid rock in an ink-black shadow and began the transfer of the bag. He had already slid everything back into a crevice when curiosity got the better of him and he removed the flowfoam container, cracked the seal, and peered in for one last glance at Neil Armstrong’s immortal footstep, the legacy of the human race that was to outlast humanity itself.

His gloves slipped on the edge of the flowfoam and he made too quick a motion to catch the container before it fell. The flowfoam stopped, but the rigid cast and footstep inside slid out with almost frictionless grace, did three slow revolutions just beyond Max’s flailing gloves, and smashed into a thousand globs of dust and shattered plaster against a sharp-edged boulder.

“Oops,” said Max.

For a moment he could only lean against the boulder and concentrate on not throwing up in his space helmet. Then a thought struck him and he brightened up considerably.

He didn’t need the footstep! The ransom was the thing; once he had that, let the lunies go diddle themselves.

Max slumped back against the boulder in a new wave of discouragement. The lunies were famous for their frontier justice but even more famous for their pragmatism. If they got their footprint back, they probably wouldn’t bear the expense and effort of sending their hit teams to Earth. But if they paid the ransom and got nothing . . .

Merde, thought Max. All this over a stupid footprint just like a million other footprints in the dust up here . . .

Max grinned behind his polarized visor, bounced down the rocky slope to a dusty bit of Mare, stomped around a bit, chose the cleanest footstep, and then did his magic with fixative and flowfoam. He took the newly preserved footstep, sealed it away, and slid the bag back in the same crevice he had chosen earlier. Then he fired up the hopper and brought it down to the dust below to let its exhaust scatter any other footsteps he had left there.

He turned in his hopper and suit to a bored attendant behind the rental counter and was back in his suite before the maid had come in to turn down his sheets and set a chocolate mint on his pillow.

One thing, he thought before dropping off to sleep. I’ll have to deal with little Swoozie before I leave on the Earthbound shuttle in the morning. She doesn’t know anything, but she knows me. No problem. He had returned the components for the deathwand to the Nikon. He’d use it once more and then dump the pieces before boarding the shuttle.

They burst in less than half an hour later—at least a dozen goons—clubbed Max senseless even before he had time to sit up and dragged him out in his silk pajamas. His toenails made slight scraping noises on the tiled floors. They dragged a chair to the center of the suite, slapped him into it, and continued to pummel him even while other men were setting up equipment around him.

He came to just as they were fitting the black and red Dante Suit over his naked body.

“Trial?” managed Max between pulped and swollen lips.

“Fuck the trial,” said the big lunie with a wild red beard and forearms bigger than Max’s thighs. “We know you done it.” The man grinned through his beard. “Besides, I’m the judge.”

“Proof?” rasped Max through the stubs of his teeth.

“Should’ve listened to your spacesuit instructor,” said the huge bald man who was wrestling the suit’s headpiece over Max’s face.

“Instructor?” Max’s attention was suddenly diverted by a glimpse of the settings on the control box that was the nexus for filaments running from the greasy-feeling Dante Suit. The words on the rheostat started at CRUSHED TESTICLES, worked their way up through SCREWDRIVER IN EYEBALL, and quickly escalated to phrases and images that Max’s mind did not want to accept. “Spacesuit instructor?” he said a second before they drove the VR peeper filaments directly and painfully into his right optic nerve.

During the brief interlude before he began screaming for the rest of his natural life, Max heard the bald man say, “Spacesuit instructor. Yeah. If you’d listened you would’ve heard him tell you that every spacesuit boot has a barcode engraved on the sole so’s we can identify and track you if you get lost. The ones back at Tranquillity Base weren’t perfect, but they led us to the suit and hopper rental. We just backtracked the hopper’s navigation memory. The footprint you left us in the bag back at the arroyo was perfect.”

Max started to say something else—something clever and legally irrefutable and salvation-winning—but the Dante Suit had stitched his lips shut. He screamed anyway. The cry echoed in his skull.

Dimly, through the nausea of panic, Max heard the red-bearded judge say, “. . . and sentence you to the rest of your natural life in this suit. May God have mercy on your putrid soul. Go ahead, Charlie, crank ’er up.”

The diamonds! thought Max with a surge of relief that made him giddy. They had thrown him into a chair directly beneath the chandelier. The Dante Suit was wrapped around his entire body now, like some clinging parasite, but his arms and hands were still free. A simple vertical leap in the one-sixth gravity would take him to the ceiling, and before they could grab him, he would have the diamonds in his hands, the bribe offered.

Coiling with the superhuman strength of absolute desperation, Max leaped for his life.

But Max was tightly wrapped in the Dante Suit, the Dante Suit was connected to the console of instruments by a dozen short cables, and two of the stocky lunies grabbed the console as Max jumped.

The Dante Suit cables were made of high-tensile carbon-carbon conducting filament. They would not have snapped if a thousand Maxes had pulled at them in a full one-gee field. They did not break now. The heavy console did not budge a centimeter. Max rose a little more than a meter and a half to the end of the cables’ reach, bounced back to his chair like a wayward balloon being tugged down by an irate child, and screamed silently as the lunies tethered him in place, threw the switch, and spun the rheostat up.

All in all, it was one puny leap for Max Kine.